Finding Aid for the Norman Thrower Papers, 1979-1989 LSC.2344
UCLA Library Special Collections
Norman Thrower papers
1979-1989
UCLA Library Special Collections
Thrower, Norman J. W. (Norman Joseph William)
LSC.2344
0.4 Linear Feet (1 box)
Norman Thrower was a professor in UCLA's geography department from 1957 to 1990, where he specialized in cartography, remote sensing, and Europe. He was the director of the (Columbus) Quincentenary Programs at the UCLA Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, and the director of the Clark Library at UCLA. The collection consists of lecture notes and pamphlets on the 1986 Halley's Comet and the subsequent Newton-Halley volume, Standing on the Shoulders of Giants: A Longer View of Newton and Halley (1990), which Thrower produced with colleagues, along with relevant correspondence.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Norman Thrower, 2001.
General note
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9982657153606533
Biography/History
Normal Thrower was born in England in 1919. He served in India during World War II and afterwards he joined the Directorate of Colonial (later Overseas) Surveys. Desiring an academic background, he completed his Bachelor of Arts degree in geography at the University of Virginia in 1953. He then earned his Ph.D. degree in geography in 1958 at the University of Wisconsin. His dissertation concerned cadastral survey systems, used to establish legal property boundaries, and it was later published by the Association of American Geographers as Original Survey and Land Subdivision: A Comparative Study of the Form and Effect of Contrasting Cadastral Surveys (1966).
Thrower joined the UCLA Department of Geography in 1957, where he specialized in cartography, remote sensing, and Europe. His research focused on the contemporary and historical aspects of cartography, including studies of orthophotomapping and Iandmark maps. He is the author and editor of several books: Maps and Man (1972), enlarged as Maps and Civilization: Cartography in Culture and Society (1996), published by the University of Chicago Press; The Complete Plattmaker: Essays on Chart, Map, and Globe Making in England in the Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries (1978); The Three Voyages of Edmond Halley in the 'Paramore', 1698-1701 (1981), published by the Hakluyt Society; Sir Francis Drake and the Famous Voyages, 1577-1580 (1984); A Leaf From the 1619 French Edition of the Mercator-Hondius World Atlas (1985); Standing on the Shoulders of Giants: A Longer View of Newton and Halley (1990); and A Buccaneer's Atlas: Basil Ringrose's South Seas Waggoner (with Derek Howse) (1992).
From 1989 to 1992, Thrower was the director of the (Columbus) Quincentenary Programs at the UCLA Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies. From 1981 to 1987, he served as the director of the Clark Library at UCLA and the UCLA Center for Seventeenth and Eighteenth Century Studies was founded during his tenure. He was also the president of The Society for the History of Discoveries from 1973 to 1975, and in 1979, he was the founding president of the California Map Society. He retired from UCLA in 1990; however, he still teaches geography courses at UCLA.
Scope and Content
The records span from 1979 to 1989 and mostly consist of lecture notes and pamphlets on Halley's Comet from 1986 and the subsequent Newton-Halley volume, Standing on the Shoulders of Giants: A Longer View of Newton and Halley (1990), which Thrower produced with colleagues, along with relevant correspondence.
Organization and Arrangement
Following Halley's Comet materials, collection is arranged by collaborator. Folders retain original titles.
Related Material
Daniel M. Popper papers (Collection 584)
Contributions of 20th Century Women to Physics: Records of the UCLA Website (Collection 458)
Margaret Galland Kivelson papers (Collection 1790)
Richard E. Lingenfelter Papers (Collection 1125)
Geographers -- United States -- Archives.; Geography teachers -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Thrower, Norman J. W. (Norman Joseph William) -- Archives; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of Geography--Faculty -- Archives
- Halley's Comet: correspondence and promotional materials, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Halley's Comet: lecture notes, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- I. Bernard Cohen correspondence, 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Cohen - Halley's Two Essays on Newton's Principia, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Alan Hugh Cook correspondence, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Cook - Edmond Halley, Surveyor and Military Engineer, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Suzanne Débarbat correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Débarbat - Newton, Halley and the Paris Observatory, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Derek Howse correspondence, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Howse - Newton, Halley and the Royal Observatory, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- David W. Waters correspondence, 1979-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Waters - Halley, FRS, Royal Navy and the Practice of Navigation, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Richard Westfall and Gerald Funk correspondence, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Westfall and Funk - Newton and Halley, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)